Finding Aid for the Collection of African Slavery in Cuba Documents LSC.2384
UCLA Library Special Collections
Collection of African slavery in Cuba documents
1852-1891
UCLA Library Special Collections
LSC.2384
2.5 linear feet (2 flat boxes)
A collection of 19th-century documents related to African slavery in Cuba. Documents include auction records, baptism records, sale documents, and other legal records. By the middle of the 16th century, enslaved Africans were colonial Cuba's primary source of labor after most of the indigenous population were killed by European diseases. Enslaved people endured forced family separation, harsh manual labor, and sexual assault. Cuba participated in the transatlantic slave trade until 1867, longer than any other region in the Americas. Sources: "African Slavery in Cuba - Manuscript Archival Collection." Description by Libros Latinos, 2019. Childs, Matt D., and Manuel Barcia. "Cuba." In The Oxford Handbook of Slavery in the Americas, edited by Mark M. Smith and Robert L. Paquette, Vol. 1. Oxford University Press, 2012. https://doi.org/10.1093/oxfordhb/9780199227990.013.0005.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Libros Latinos, 2019.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9996976026206533
Biographical / Historical
By the middle of the 16th century, enslaved Africans were colonial Cuba's primary source of labor after most of the indigenous population were killed by European diseases. Enslaved people endured forced family separation, harsh manual labor, and sexual assault. Cuba participated in the transatlantic slave trade until 1867, longer than any other region in the Americas. In 1880, Cuba passed their Patronato Law that established a set date for the abolition of slavery. Under this law enslaved people were required to complete an eight-year period of unpaid indentured servitude where formerly enslaved people were called patrocinados and enslavers were called patronos. Slavery in Cuba was not officially abolished by Spanish royal decree until 1886, two years before the original planned date under Patronato Slavery.
Sources:
"African Slavery in Cuba - Manuscript Archival Collection." Description by Libros Latinos, 2019.
Childs, Matt D., and Manuel Barcia. "Cuba." In The Oxford Handbook of Slavery in the Americas, edited by Mark M. Smith and Robert L. Paquette, Vol. 1. Oxford University Press, 2012. https://doi.org/10.1093/oxfordhb/9780199227990.013.0005.
Scope and Contents
A collection of 19th-century documents related to African slavery in Cuba. Documents include auction records, baptism records, sale documents, and other legal records.
Arrangement
This collection has been arranged chronologically.
Slavery -- Cuba; Indentured servants
- Manuscript of an enslaved Black man in the Royal Jail, 1852 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Document regarding liberty of Luisa, 1856 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Scope and Contents
  Luisa was an enslaved Black person.
- About the purchase of an enslaved female, 1857 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- About the auction/remate del Deposito General de Esclavos, 1860 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Libertad de esclava and venta de esclava, circa 1860-1869 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Venta de esclavo and venta de esclavo, circa 1860-1869 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Libertad de esclava and venta de esclava, circa 1860-1869 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Venta de 3 esclavos, circa 1860-1869 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Manuscript, venta de esclava, female, 400 escudos, circa 1860-1869 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Manuscript, libertad de esclava female and libertad de esclavo male, circa 1860-1869 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Manuscript, venta de esclava, female, 200 escudos and libertad de esclava female, 1400 escudos, circa 1860-1869 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Manuscript, venta de esclava, female, 1200 escudos, circa 1860-1869 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Manuscript mentioning "esclavos" on official letterhead of "Coma de entradas de S. Felipe y Santiago", 1862 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Manuscript regarding slave auctioneer of a slave depository and the annulment of an auction, 1863 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  A captain general is involved.
- Detailed report on baptism for "negros bozales emancipados", 1864 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Legal manuscript regarding an inquiry made by a slave auctioneer of a slave depository on the nullification of a slave auction, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  Abuses are also discussed in the manuscript.
- Libertad de esclavo, 1864 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Legal manuscript regarding slave auctioneer of a slave depository., 1865 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  Discusses a failure to submit slaves to a depository, rendering a slave auction invalid.
- Venta de esclava, female 25, and venta de esclava, female, 20, 1866 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Venta de esclavo, female 7, and libertad of 4 enslaved people, 1866 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  Libertad includes a female aged 26 and her three children, two of which are described as "chino."
- Libertad de esclava, 1866 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Document discussing a free and previously enslaved African, 1866 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Document granting freedom to a six-year-old girl, 1866 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Venta de esclava and libertad of a "china criolla," aged 40, 1866 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Manuscript, libertad de esclava, female, 26 and libertad de esclava, female, 25 and her daughter, 6 months old, 1866 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Manuscript, libertad de esclava female, 1866 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Manuscript, venta de esclava, female, 27 "who knows how to wash and iron", 1866 (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Manuscript, libertad de eslcavo, 13-month-old baby, 1866 (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Three documents regarding the "Brooks Brothers", 1866-1874 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  The first documents the freedom of a male slave by Brooks & Company; the second is an 1874 legal manuscript from the consulate of the United States in Paris, France, discussing one of the Brooks Brothers, bearing several seals from the Consul General; the third document is written in 1871 New York by a French law firm discussing Brooks & Company as well as other family members.
- Extensive solicitation to open a brotherhood for people of color in Regla, Havana, 1867 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  The request is made by Abraham Gomes, described as Black/Moreno of old age.
- Death certificates for free and unfree Black persons, 1886 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- 40 death certificates for "Morenos" and "Pardos", 1886-1889 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  The majority are described as "natural de" Africa.
- Sale of enslaved black female, aged 24 with her 1-year-old baby, 1869 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Freedom of a 32-year-old enslaved female, 1869 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Sale of two enslaved males, 1869 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Venta de esclava, 30 and venta de two esclavos, aged 25 and 22, 1869 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Venta de esclavo de Africa, aged 38 and venta of a 46-year-old enslaved female, 1869 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Venta de 19 esclavos and venta of an enslaved female, aged 22, 1869 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Manuscript, libertad, granting the freedom of a Black enslaved female, 20 years old, 1869 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Manuscript, venta de esclava, 20 years old, 1869 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Manuscript, venta de esclavos, female, 21 years old, African enslaved male, 44, 1869 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Manuscript, venta de esclavo, 21 years old, 1869 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Manuscript, venta de esclavo, 18 years old, 1869 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Manuscript, libertad de esclava female, 26, 1869 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Baptismal document of a Lucumi enslaved person from Guanabo near Havana, 1871 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Notice of an enslaved Black person being sent to Puerto Rico, 1871 (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Documents regarding a Black prisoner in a "castillo" on official letterhead of "Comandancia General del Distrito de Matanzas", 1872 (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Pagare for the transport of five "negros alquilados", 1873 (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Police document regarding Moreno "Joaquin Diaz", 1875 (Box 2, Folder 19)
- Manuscript, a young girl is certified by a doctor as belonging to the "raza blanca", 1875 (Box 2, Folder 20)
- Manuscript re: baptism of a girl belonging to the "white class", 1875 (Box 2, Folder 21)
- Pagare for the payment of an enslaved person, 1876 (Box 2, Folder 22)
- Manuscript, baby classified as having characteristics of the white race, 1876 (Box 2, Folder 23)
- Manuscript el "parbulo", son of a Black woman who belongs to el "clase de pobre" being admitted to Real Casa de Beneficencia y Maternidad, 1877 (Box 2, Folder 24)
- Manuscript re: a Black man ("pardo") Juan Ricardo Valdez, 1877 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  Juan Ricardo Valdez who says he was baptized in February 1869, but no records can be found in the years 1868/1869.
- Manuscript re: a girl who offers all "the characteristics and signs" she belongs to the "white race" as observed by the medical doctor "de la Casa", 1877 (Box 2, Folder 26)
- Manuscript regarding a Moreno woman being taken to an asylum, 1881 (Box 2, Folder 27)
- Manuscript regarding Salvador, an enslaved Moreno man, 1883 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  Features "Junta Provincial de Patronato Matanzas" stamp.
- Six burial notices for "Morenos" and "Pardos", 1886-1889 (Box 2, Folder 29)
- A wedding manuscript detailing the wedding of Juan de Dios Llanes and Florinda Hernandez y Gil, 1891 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  Juan de Dios LLanes is described as "Pardo" (Black) and Florinda Hernandez y Gil, described as white. Includes some history of Juan de Dios Llanes.
- Manuscript regarding Angel, an enslaved Moreno person, 1891 (Box 2, Folder 31)